Alfred Tennyson Collection
Alfred Tennyson Collection
1852-1875
Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892.
10 items (SC)
Papers of the British poet. Includes six outgoing items of correspondence, one of which is addressed to Tennyson's aunt by marriage, Lady Jane Franklin, while three others are to Sophie Cracroft, all concerning family matters.
149336
Biographical History
Alfred Tennyson (1809-1892) was a British poet who served as Poet Laureate of the United Kingdom from 1850-1892. Notable works include In Memoriam (1850), The Charge of the Light Brigade (1854), and Idylls of the King (1859).
Selected Poems
1830 "The Kraken"
1833 Ulysses
1842 (ca.) Break, Break, Break
1847 Tears, Idle Tears
1850 In Memoriam
1851 "The Eagle"
1854 The Charge of the Light Brigade
1859 Idylls of the King
1889 Crossing the Bar
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alfred Tennyson Collection comprises 8 items of correspondence and two portraits of the English poet (1809-1892). The earliest letter, addressed to Lady Jane Franklin, wife of explorer John Franklin, invites Tennyson's aunt by marriage to the christening of his son. Three other letters addressed to Sophia Cracroft, companion of Lady Franklin, discuss the health of Tennyson's wife Emily, the couple's inability to accept Lady Franklin's offer of a house, and Sophy's kindness in sending the Tennysons two remembrances of Lady Franklin following her death. A letter (20 Apr 1867) to an unspecified correspondent grants permission to use extracts from some Tennyson poems, noting however that "In Memoriam is an anonymous work not to be meddled with."
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains two series: Correspondence and Portraits. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Cracroft, Sophia, 1816-1892.; Franklin, Jane, 1791-1875.; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892.; Tennyson, Emily Sellwood Tennyson, Baroness, 1813-1896.; Tennyson family.; Poets, English -- 19th century.; Poets, English -- Family relationships.; Correspondence.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Jane Griffith Franklin ("Dear Lady Franklin"), 20 Sep 1852 (Sc 65)
  - "Madam", 20 Apr 1867 (Sc 65)
  - "Sir", 08 Jul 1874 (Sc 65)
  - Sophia Cracroft ("My dear Sophy"), 22 Oct 1874 (Sc 65)
  - Sophia Cracroft ("My dear Sophy"), 10 Nov 1874 (Sc 65)
  - Sophia Cracroft ("My dear Sophy"), 16 Dec 1875 (Sc 65)
  - "Dear Sir", 30 Apr 1876 (Sc 65)
  - Leonard Hess, 11 Apr 1885; Tennyson's response through unnamed third party (Sc 65)
- Portraits
  - Engraving (Sc 65)
  - Photograph, Elliott & Fry (Sc 65)